<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6020 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6020.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6241 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7317 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7317.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<!--<?rfc strict="no"?> -->

<rfc category="std"
     ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-ietf-netconf-zerotouch-latest">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="Zero Touch">Zero Touch Provisioning for NETCONF Call Home</title>
        <author initials="K.W." surname="Watsen" fullname="Kent Watsen">
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <email>kwatsen@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="J.C." surname="Clarke" fullname="Joe Clarke">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <email>jclarke@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="M.A." surname="Abrahamsson" fullname="Mikael Abrahamsson">
            <organization>T-Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <email>"mikael.abrahamsson@t-systems.se</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date/>
        <area>Operations</area>
        <workgroup>NETCONF Working Group</workgroup>
        <keyword>zerotouch</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>This draft presents a technique for establishing a
            secure NETCONF or RESTCONF connection between a newly deployed 
            device, configured with just its factory 
            default settings, and its rightful owner's network
            management system (NMS).</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
      <section title="Introduction">

        <t>A fundamental business requirement is to reduce 
        costs where possible.  For network operators, deploying
        devices to many locations can be a significant cost, as
        sending trained specialists to each site to do installations
        is both cost prohibitive and does not scale.</t>

        <t>This document defines bootstrapping strategies enabling a device to 
        securely obtain bootstrapping data with no installer input beyond racking
        the device and applying power.  This bootstrapping data directs
        the device to install a boot image and an initial configuration,
        which enables the establishment of a NETCONF <xref target="RFC6241"/>
        or RESTCONF <xref target="draft-ietf-netconf-restconf"/>
        connection to its rightful owner's network management system (NMS).</t>

        <t>In order to enable a NETCONF or RESTCONF connection to be
        established,  the initial configuration should include
        settings such as enabling the NETCONF/RESTCONF service,
        including parameters needed to support an NMS-initiated
        or device-initiated connection, and configuring a local
        administrator account.  Examples used in this draft 
        illustrate this using models defined by <xref target="RFC7317"/>
        and <xref target="draft-ietf-netconf-server-model"/>.</t>

        <section title="Use Cases" anchor="use-cases">
          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Connecting to a remotely administered network
                <list style="empty">
                  <t>This use-case involves scenarios, such as a remote
                  branch office or convenience store, whereby a device
                  connects as an access gateway to an ISP's network.
                  Assuming it is not possible to customize the ISP's
                  network, and with no other nearby device to leverage,
                  the device has no recourse but to reach out to the
                  public Internet for a well-known service it can
                  bootstrap off of.</t>
                </list>
              </t>
              <t>Connecting to a locally administered network
                <list style="empty">
                  <t>This use-case covers all other scenarios
                  and differs only in that the device may
                  additionally leverage nearby devices, which may direct 
                  it to use a local service to bootstrap off of. 
                  If no such site-specific information is available, or
                  the device is unable to use the information provided,
                  it can then reach out to network just as it would for
                  the remotely administered network use-case.</t>
                </list>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
<!--
          <t><vspace blankLines="30"/></t>
-->
        </section>


        <section title="Terminology" anchor="terminology">
          <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
          and "OPTIONAL" in the sections below are to be interpreted
          as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

          <t>This document defines the following terms:
            <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
              <t hangText="Artifact:">The term "artifact" is used throughout to represent
              bootstrapping data that can be encoded outside of the RESTCONF protocol.  For example,
              an artifact may be a file on disk or a message in another protocol.  Unless
              used inside a secure protocol, artifacts must be signed and need to be
              provided along with an Owner Certificate and an Ownership Voucher (see terms),
              so the a device can validate the artifact's signature to its Rightful Owner (see term).</t>
              <t hangText="Bootstrap Server:">The term "bootstrap server" is used within
              this document to mean any RESTCONF server implementing the YANG module
              defined in <xref target="yang-module"/>.</t>
              <t hangText="Device:">The term "device" is used throughout this document
              to refer to the network element that needs to be bootstrapped.  The device
              is the RESTCONF client to a Bootstrap Server (see above) and, at the end of
              bootstrapping process, the device is the NETCONF or RESTCONF server to a
              deployment-specific NMS.  See <xref target="device-details"/> for more
              information about devices.</t>
              <t hangText="Network Management System (NMS):">The acronym "NMS" is used
              throughout this document to refer to the deployment specific management
              system that the bootstrapping process ultimately connects the devices to.
              From a device's perspective, when the bootstrapping process has completed,
              the NMS is a NETCONF or RESTCONF client.</t>
              <t hangText="Owner:">See Rightful Owner.</t>
              <t hangText="Owner Certificate:">An owner certificate, signed by the
              device's manufacturer or delegate, binds an owner identity to the owner's private
              key, which the owner can subsequently use to sign artifacts.  The owner
              certificate is an X.509 certificate encoding the owner's identity
              in the Subject field of the X.509 certificate.  The owner certificate
              is used by devices only when validating owner signatures on Signed Data (see term).</t>
              <t hangText="Ownership Voucher:">An ownership voucher, signed by the
              device's manufacturer or delegate, binds an owner identity to one or more
              device identities (e.g., serial numbers).  The ownership voucher is used
              by devices only when validating owner signatures on Signed Data (see term).</t>
              <t hangText="Redirect Server:">The term "redirect server" is used to refer to
              a Bootstrap Server (see above) that only returns Redirect Information (<xref
              target="information-types"/>).</t>
              <t hangText="Rightful Owner:">The rightful owner of a device is the person or
              organization that purchased the device.  How ownership can be conveyed to a
              device is described in <xref target="ownership"/>.</t>
              <t hangText="Secure Redirect:">Secure redirect is like an HTTP Redirect
              except that it also returns TLS certificates that can be used as trust anchors
              to validate the secure connection to the Bootstrap Server the device is being redirected to.</t>
              <t hangText="Signed Data:">The term "signed data" is used throughout to mean
              data that has been signed by a device's Rightful Owner's private key.  Any time
              data is signed, it must be presented along with an Owner Certificate and
              Ownership Voucher (see terms).</t>
              <t hangText="Unsigned Data:">The term "unsigned data" is used throughout to mean
              data that has not been signed by a device's Rightful Owner's private key.  The
              option to use unsigned data is available only when the data is obtained over a
              secure connection, such as to a Redirect Server or a Bootstrap Server (see terms).</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Tree Diagrams" anchor="tree-diagram">
          <t>A simplified graphical representation of the data models
          is used in this document.  The meaning of the symbols in
          these diagrams is as follows:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Brackets "[" and "]" enclose list keys.</t>
              <t>Braces "{" and "}" enclose feature names, and indicate
              that the named feature must be present for the subtree
              to be present.</t>
              <t>Abbreviations before data node names: "rw" means
              configuration (read-write) and "ro" state data
              (read-only).</t>
              <t>Symbols after data node names: "?" means an optional
              node, "!" means a presence container, and "*" denotes a
              list and leaf-list.</t>
              <t>Parentheses enclose choice and case nodes, and case
              nodes are also marked with a colon (":").</t>
              <t>Ellipsis ("...") stands for contents of subtrees that
              are not shown.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>  <!-- end Introduction -->

      <section title="Guiding Principles" anchor="guiding-principles">
        <t>This section provides overarching principles guiding the solution presented in this document.</t>
        <section title="Trust Anchors" anchor="trust-anchors">
          <t>A device in its factory default state can only trust remote keys for which it has preconfigured trust 
          anchors.  For instance, the device may have a trust anchor (e.g., a X.509 certificate) for
          when authenticating a very specific HTTPS server, and another trust anchor for when validating
          boot-image files, and yet another trust anchor for when verifying software licenses.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Conveying Trust">
          <t>Trust can be conveyed by either transport level security or artifact signing.  For instance, if a device
          connects to an HTTPS server, authenticating the TLS certificate to a known trust anchor, then any data
          the device receives from the HTTPS server can also be trusted.  Likewise, if a device
          can authenticate the signature over some data to a known trust anchor, then that data can also be
          trusted.  In general, any data obtained from a trusted source MAY be trusted and, any data obtained
          from an untrusted source MUST NOT be trusted.</t>
          <t>It is possible but unnecessary to provide signed data over a secure connection.  For instance,
          a device connecting to a trusted HTTPS server may retrieve data that has been signed by its rightful
          owner, but this is not required, as the device is already assured by the server that its data was
          staged by its rightful owner.  That said, when an insecure connection is used (e.g., DHCP), the 
          device has no choice but to require that the data be signed, in order to trust the data.</t> 
        </section>
        <section title="Ownership" anchor="ownership">
          <t>The goal of this document is to enable a device to connect with its rightful owner's NMS.   This entails
          the manufacturer being able to track who owns which devices (out of the scope of this document), as well
          as an ability to convey that information to devices (in scope).  Matching the two ways to convey trust, this 
          document provides both a protocol-oriented solution as well as an artifact based solution for conveying ownership.</t>
          <t>The protocol based solution conveys ownership by API contract, in that
          the server asserts that it will only return data that it is sure was staged by that device's rightful
          owner.  How ownership for a device is assured is out of scope of this document.</t>
          <t>The artifact based solution involves the manufacturer signing an owner
          key and then later, when the ownership for devices is established, the manufacturer signing a voucher
          that assigns those devices to the owner, and then the owner using their private key to sign the artifacts.
          Thus, from the device's perspective, it can use the presented "ownership voucher" to validate the
          presented "owner certificate", which it can then use to validate the signature over the presented
          artifact.</t>
          <t>The YANG module in <xref target="yang-module"/> includes grouping statements defining the
          format for the owner certificates and ownership vouchers used by the bootstrapping solution
          presented in this document.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Information Types" anchor="information-types">
          <t>This document presumes there exists two types of zero touch information: redirect information and bootstrapping
          information.  Either type of data may by accessed as unsigned data over a secure connection to a 
          trusted server (e.g., HTTPS), or as signed artifacts obtained via an insecure method (DHCP server, 
          removable storage device, etc.).</t> 
          <t>The redirect information type of data provides two bits of information: bootstrap server 
          locations and trust anchors.  The trust anchors are provided to enable the device to 
          authentic the specified bootstrap servers (TLS certificate-based authentication).
          This is what distinguishes this technique from a standard HTTP Redirect and why it
          may sometimes be called "secure redirect".</t>
          <t>The bootstrap information type of data provides information describing the
          boot-image and configuration the device should be running, in order to be considered
          bootstrapped.  The boot-image information is optional but, if it is provided, the
          device should install the boot image prior to installing the configuration.</t> 
          <t>The YANG module in <xref target="yang-module"/> includes grouping statements defining the
          format for redirect and bootstrap information types  used by the bootstrapping solution
          presented in this document.</t>
        </section>
      </section>   <!-- end guiding principles -->

      <section title="Sources for Bootstrapping Data" anchor="sources">
        <t>Following are the sources of bootstrapping data that are referenced by the
        workflow presented in <xref target="device-powers-on"/>.  Other sources for
        bootstrapping information may be described in other documents, so long as the principles
        for when the bootstrapping data needs to be signed or not are enforced.</t>
        <t>Each of the descriptions below show how the bootstrapping data needs to be handled in a manner
        consistent with the guiding principles in <xref target="guiding-principles"/>.</t>
        <t>For devices supporting more than one source for bootstrapping data, no particular sequencing
        order has to be observed, as each source is equally secure, in that the chain of trust
        always goes back to the same root of trust, the manufacturer.</t>
        <section title="Removable Storage">
          <t>A device may attempt to read bootstrapping information from a directly attached
          removable storage device.  This information would most likely have to be signed, as
          removable storage devices are generally not trustworthy.</t>
          <t>The information loaded from a removable storage device may redirect the device to a
          bootstrap server (i.e., redirect information) or it may provide the boot image and 
          configuration (i.e., bootstrapping information) directly.  For when providing the
          information directly, even the raw boot image file could be on the removable
          storage device, making it a fully self-standing solution.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="DHCP Server">
          <t>A device may attempt to read bootstrapping information from a DHCP server (e.g., DHCP
          options).  This information would have to be signed, as the DHCP protocol is not a secure protocol.</t>
          <t>The information may again be either redirect or bootstrapping information.  If bootstrapping 
          information is provided, the URI to the boot image would have to specify a file server 
          (e.g., ftp://, tftp://, etc.), as DHCP servers do not themselves distribute files.
          Note that it is acceptable for boot images to be fetched using an insecure protocol
          when having an embedded signature, as is commonly the case.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Internet Based Service">
          <t>A device may attempt to read bootstrapping information from a trusted Internet based
          service.  The hosted information would not have to be signed, as the device would authenticate
          the service when establishing a secure connection to it, using trust anchors the device
          is manufactured with in its factory default state.</t>
          <t>This document defines a RESTCONF API for a bootstrap server that may be hosted on the
          Internet.  The YANG module describing this API is provided in <xref target="yang-module"/>.</t>
          <t>The information may again redirect the device to a bootstrap server (i.e., redirect information) or it
          may direct the device to load a boot image and a configuration (i.e., bootstrapping information).
          If bootstrapping information is provided, the URI to the boot image would not have to be
          to a server the device has a trust anchor for, assuming the boot image has an embedded signature,
          as is commonly the case.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

<!--
      <section title="Actors and Roles" anchor="actors-and-roles">
        <section title="Bootstrap Server" anchor="bootstrap-server">
          <t>A Bootstrap Server hosts bootstrapping information staged by the
          rightful owner of a device.  A Bootstrap Server MAY return Redirect
          Information or Bootstrap Information (see <xref target="information-types"/>).</t>
          <t>In practice, Internet-based servers will most likely (for privacy
          reasons) only return Redirect Information, pointing devices to deployment-specific
          servers that would only return Bootstrap Information.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Device" anchor="device">
          <t>Devices supporting Zero Touch will only attempt the
          bootstrapping process when booting with its factory default
          configuration.</t>
          <t>See <xref target="device-details"/> for details on devices.</t>

            <t>The devices supporting NETCONF Zero Touch will only attempt the
            bootstrapping process when booting with its factory default 
            configuration.  As illustrated above, the bootstrapping process
            consists of three interactions:
              <list style="numbers">
                <t>When joining the network, the device will attempt to configure
                IP networking from a DHCP server.  If the device is able to reach
                a DHCP server, it may discover additional bootstrapping information.
                The additional bootstrapping information consists of one or more additional
                Bootstrap Servers the device should try to connect to.</t>
                <t>The device sequentially processes its list of Bootstrap Servers,
                prioritizing any that might have been learned from the DHCP
                server.  Once the device has successfully configured itself using
                the bootstrapping information, it notifies the bootstrapping 
                server for monitoring purposes.</t>
                <t>Assuming the bootstrapping information configures the device
                appropriately, the device will initiate a NETCONF Call Home
                connection <xref target="draft-ietf-netconf-call-home"/>.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>More information about Devices is in <xref target="device"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="DHCP Server">
            <t>This draft assumes the use of a DHCP server but, in reality, the
            solution is not intrinsically tied to using a DHCP server.  Any
            mechanism or combination of mechanisms that can provide dynamic
            networking assignment would equally do.</t>
            <t>Assuming the use of DHCP, this draft defines a specific DHCP
            Option for the discovering of addition bootstrapping information.
            More information about the Zero Touch DHCP Option is in
            <xref target="zerotouch-info-option"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Network Management System">
            <t>The NMS is a term used here loosely to represent any system,
            or collection of systems, deployed by a business organization to 
            manage its devices.  An NMS being able to establish a secure NETCONF 
            connection with devices purchased by its organization is the ultimate
            goal of this solution presented by this draft.  More information about
            the Network Management System is in <xref target="nms"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Manufacturer">
            <t>Manufacturers manufacture the devices supporting NETCONF Zero Touch.
            To support this solution, Manufacturers must support a one-time enrollment
            process per business organization owning the NMS.  Manufacturers must also support
            sending additional information to the business organization about the 
            devices that have been shipped for device orders it places.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Redirect Server" anchor="redirect-server">
        </section>
        <section title="Rightful Owner" anchor="rightful-owner">
        </section>
      </section>
-->
      <section title="Workflow Overview">

        <t>The zero touch solution presented in this document is conceptualized
        to be composed of the workflows described in this section.  Implementations
        MAY vary in details.</t>

        <section title="Onboarding and Ordering Devices" anchor="onboarding-and-ordering">
          <t>The following diagram illustrates key interactions that occur from when
          a manufacturer or delegate onboards a prospective device owner to when the manufacturer
          ships devices for an order placed by the prospective device owner.</t>
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                              +-----------+
+------------+                |Prospective|                  +---+
|Manufacturer|                |   Owner   |                  |NMS|
+------------+                +-----------+                  +---+
      |                             |                          |
      |                             |                          |
      |  1. enroll me please        |                          |
      #<----------------------------|                          |
      #                             |                          |
      #  account credentials and/or |                          |
      #  and/or owner certificate   |                          |
      #---------------------------->|                          |
      |                             |                          |
      |                             |                          |
      |                             |                          |
      |  2. get IDevID trust anchor |                          |
      |<----------------------------#  set IDevID trust anchor |
      |                             #------------------------->|
      |                             |                          |
      |                             |                          |
      |  3. place device order      |                          |
      |<----------------------------#  model devices           |
      |                             #------------------------->|
      |                             |                          |
      |  4. ship devices and send   |                          |
      |     device identifiers and  |                          |
      |     ownership vouchers      |                          |
      |---------------------------->#  set device identifiers  |
      |                             #  and ownership vouchers  |
      |                             #------------------------->|
      |                             |                          |
      |                             |                          |
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>The interactions in the above diagram are described below.
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>A prospective owner establishes a trust relationship
              with a manufacturer in order to place zero touch orders.
              Assuming the manufacturer or delegate hosts a secure redirect
              server, this onbording interaction might entail the creation of
              an online account that the owner can use to configure
              redirect information for future device orders.  Alternatively,
              the onbording interaction may include the manufacturer signing
              an owner certificate (see <xref target="terminology"/>), to be used 
              for bootstrapping devices not using the manufacturer's redirect
              server.  The onboarding interaction may also do both, giving
              the choice to the owner for how specific devices should
              bootstrap.</t>
              <t>The prospective owner downloads from the manufacturer the X.509
              based trust anchor certificate that can be used to validate
              the IDevID certificate <xref target="Std-802.1AR-2009"/> the
              devices will present as their SSH host key or TLS server certificate,
              when establishing a NETCONF or RESTCONF connection with the
              prospective owner's deployment-specific NMS.</t>
              <t>Some time later, the prospective owner places an order
              with the manufacturer, perhaps with a special flag checked
              for zero touch handling.  At this time, perhaps before
              placing the order, the owner may model the devices in their
              NMS. That is, create virtual objects for the devices with no
              real-world device associations.  For instance the model can
              be used to simulate the device's location in the network and
              the configuration it should have when fully operational.</t>
              <t>When the manufacturer ships the devices for the order,
              the manufacturer notifies the owner of the devices' unique identifiers
              and shipping destinations, which the owner can use to stage the
              network for when the devices powers on.  Additionally,  the
              manufacturer may send a ownership voucher assigning ownership
              of those devices to the rightful owner and/or configure backend
              systems so the secure redirect service can associate the 
              redirect information to the devices.  The owner sets this
              information on the NMS, perhaps binding specific device identifiers
              and ownership vouchers (if supported) to specific modeled devices.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>


        <section title="Owner Stages the Network for Bootstrap">
          <t>The following diagram illustrates how an owner stages the
          network for bootstrapping devices.</t> 
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                   +----------+   +------------+           
                   |Deployment|   |Manufacturer|   +------+
                   | Specific |   |   Hosted   |   | Local|   +---------+
          +---+    |Bootstrap |   |  Redirect  |   | DHCP |   |Removable|
          |NMS|    |  Server  |   |   Server   |   |Server|   | Storage |
          +---+    +----------+   +------------+   +------+   +---------+
            |           |               |             |            |
   activate |           |               |             |            |
   modeled  |           |               |             |            |
1. device   |           |               |             |            |
----------->|           |               |             |            |
            |           |               |             |            |
            | 2. stage bootstrap        |             |            |
            |    information            |             |            |
            |---------->|               |             |            |
            |           |               |             |            |
            | 3. (optional) configure   |             |            |
            |    redirect server        |             |            |
            |-------------------------->|             |            |
            |           |               |             |            |
            |           |               |             |            |
            | 4. (optional) configure DHCP server     |            |
            |---------------------------------------->|            |
            |           |               |             |            |
            |           |               |             |            |
            | 5. (optional) store bootstrapping artifacts on media |
            |----------------------------------------------------->|
            |           |               |             |            |
            |           |               |             |            |
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>The interactions in the above diagram are described below.
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>Having previously modeled the devices, including setting their
              fully operational configurations, associating device identifiers
              and ownership vouchers (if supported), the owner may "activate"
              one or more modeled devices.  That is, tell the NMS to perform
              the steps necessary to prepare for when the real-world devices
              are powered up.</t>
              <t>One thing the NMS must do is configure the deployment specific
              bootstrap server.  Illustrated here as an external component, the
              bootstrap server may be implemented as an internal component of the NMS itself.
              Configuring the bootstrap server may occur via a programmatic API
              not defined by this document.  This step sets signed or unsigned
              bootstrap information, as shown in <xref target="api-examples"/>,
              for the devices being activated.   The configuration set MUST be
              at least enough to enable a secure NETCONF or RESTCONF connection
              to be established and MAY be the device's fully operational
              configuration.</t>
              <t>If it is desired to use a manufacturer or delegate hosted
              redirect service to supply the bootstrapping information,
              the redirect server would need to be configured to supply the redirect
              information to the devices.  Configuring the redirect server may
              occur via a programmatic API not defined by this document.
              This step sets signed or unsigned redirect information, as shown
              in <xref target="api-examples"/>, for the devices being activated. 
              The redirect information MUST set the IP address or hostname of the
              deployment specific bootstrap server and MAY set the X.509
              trust anchor certificate to authenticate the bootstrap server's
              TLS certificate.</t>
              <t>If it is desired to use a DHCP server to supply bootstrapping
              information, the DHCP server would need to be configured to supply the redirect
              information to the devices.  Configuring the DHCP server may
              occur via a programmatic API (not defined by this document). Since
              DHCP is an insecure protocol, the information would have to be
              signed.  That is, either signed redirect or signed bootstrap
              information, as shown in <xref target="api-examples"/>.</t>
              <t>If it is desired to use a removable storage device (e.g., USB
              flash drive) to supply bootstrapping information, the information
              would need to be placed onto it.  Since a removable storage device
              is insecure, the information would have to be signed.  That is,
              either signed redirect or signed bootstrap information, as shown
              in <xref target="api-examples"/>.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Device Powers On" anchor="device-powers-on">
          <t>The following diagram illustrates how a device might behave
          when powered on.  Note that this is merely exemplary, subject to
          which bootstrapping strategies the device supports, which may be
          more or less than depicted below.</t>
          <t>This example sequences the sources of information (see
          <xref target="sources"/>) based on locality, or how "close" to the
          device the data is.  Whether this sequence makes sense for a
          specific type of device needs to be determined by the manufacturer.</t>
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[

                                    +------------+   +----------+
                         +------+   |Manufacturer|   |Deployment|
           +---------+   | Local|   |   Hosted   |   | Specific |
+------+   |Removable|   | DHCP |   |  Redirect  |   |Bootstrap |   +---+
|Device|   | Storage |   |Server|   |   Server   |   |  Server  |   |NMS|
+------+   +---------+   +------+   +------------+   +----------+   +---+
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   | 1. if not factory default, then exit. |               |          |
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   | 2. check   |            |             |               |          |
   #----------->|            |             |               |          |
   # if signed redirect information found  |               |  web-    |
   #------------------------------------------------------>#    hook  |
   #    either NMS-initiated connection    |               #--------->#
   #<-----------------------------------------------------------------#
   #    or device-initiated connection     |               |          |
   #----------------------------------------------------------------->|
   # else if signed bootstrap information found (call home)|          |
   #----------------------------------------------------------------->|
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   | 3. Get IP assignment    |             |               |          |
   #------------------------>|             |               |          |
   # if signed redirect information found                  |  web-    |
   #------------------------------------------------------>#    hook  |
   #    either NMS-initiated connection    |               #--------->#
   #<-----------------------------------------------------------------#
   #    or device-initiated connection     |               |          |
   #----------------------------------------------------------------->|
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   | 4. check   |            |             |               |          |
   #-------------------------------------->|               |          |
   # if signed or unsigned redirect information found      |  web-    |
   #------------------------------------------------------>#    hook  |
   #    either NMS-initiated connection    |               #--------->#
   #<-----------------------------------------------------------------#
   #    or device-initiated connection     |               |          |
   #----------------------------------------------------------------->|
   |            |            |             |               |          |
   |
   | 5. loop or wait for manual provisioning.
   | 
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>The interactions in the above diagram are described below.
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>Upon power being applied, the device's bootstrapping logic
              first checks to see if it is running in its factory default
              state.  If it has a modified state, then the bootstrapping
              logic would exit and none to the following interactions
              would occur.</t>
              <t>If the device is able to load bootstrapping data from a removable
              storage device (e.g., USB flash drive), it might choose to do so
              first.  The removable storage may have either signed redirect
              information or signed bootstrap information, as shown in 
              <xref target="artifact-examples"/>.
                <list style="dash">
                  <t>In the case that signed redirect
                  information is found, the device would use it to established
                  a connection to the deployment-specific bootstrap server, which
                  would set its boot image and configure it to enable connections
                  with the deployment-specific NMS to be established.  If the
                  bootstrap supports notifying (e.g., via a web-hook) external systems when a device
                  sends its bootstrap-complete notification (<xref target="yang-module"/>),
                  it would be possible for the NMS to initiate a NETCONF or RESTCONF
                  connection to the device.  Otherwise the configuration could configure the
                  device it initiate a NETCONF or RESTCONF call home <xref
                  target="draft-ietf-netconf-call-home"/> connection to the
                  deployment-specific NMS.</t>
                  <t>In the case that signed bootstrap
                  information is found, the device would use it to set its boot
                  image and initial configuration, which would have to direct it to
                  initiate a NETCONF or RESTCONF call home connection to the 
                  deployment-specific NMS.</t>
                  <t>If the device is unable to bootstrap
                  using any of the information on the removable storage device, it would
                  proceed to the next source of bootstrapping information, if any.</t>
                </list>
              </t>
              <t>If the device is able to load bootstrapping data from a DHCP
              server, when obtaining a DHCP assignment, it may receive signed
              redirect information in a DHCP Option (<xref target="iana-considerations"/>).
              The device would process the signed redirect information in the same
              manner as described above for when it's loaded from a removable storage
              device.  If the device is unable to bootstrap using information provided
              by a DHCP server, it would proceed to the next source of bootstrapping
              information, if any.</t>
              <t>If the device is able to obtain a routable address to the Internet,
              it may attempt to establish a connection to a redirect server that is
              set by its factory default state (<xref target="factory-defaults"/>).
              These connections would use the RESTCONF API described in this document
              and would be secured using trust anchors also set in the device's factory
              default state.  The redirect server may provide signed or unsigned
              redirect information.  In either case, the device would process the
              redirect information in the same manner as described above for when it's
              loaded from a removable storage device.  If the device is unable to
              bootstrap using information provided by any redirect servers, it
              would proceed to the next source of bootstrapping information, if any.</t> 
              <t>If no more sources of bootstrapping information are available, the device
              may fall into a loop to try again or it may provide manageability
              interfaces for manual configuration (e.g., CLI, HTTP, NETCONF, etc.).</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>


      <section title="Device Details" anchor="device-details">

          <t>Devices supporting Zero Touch MUST have the preconfigured
          factory default state and bootstrapping logic described
          in the following sections.</t>

          <section title="Factory Default State" anchor="factory-defaults">
            <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
  +------------------------------------------------------------------+
  |                             <device>                             |
  |                                                                  |
  |   +----------------------------------------------------------+   |
  |   |                   <read-only storage>                    |   |
  |   |                                                          |   |
  |   | 1. list of public Internet Bootstrap Servers             |   |
  |   | 2. list of trust anchor certs for Bootstrap Servers      |   |
  |   | 3. trust anchor cert for owner certificates              |   |
  |   | 4. trust anchor cert for device ownership vouchers       |   |
  |   | 5. IDevID cert & associated intermediate certificate(s)  |   |
  |   +----------------------------------------------------------+   |
  |                                                                  |
  |                    +----------------------+                      |
  |                    |   <secure storage>   |                      |
  |                    |                      |                      |
  |                    |  6. private key      |                      |
  |                    +----------------------+                      |
  |                                                                  |
  +------------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>Devices that support loading bootstrapping information from the Internet
              (see <xref target="sources"/>) MUST be manufactured with a
              list of default Bootstrap Servers.  Each Bootstrap Server may be identified
              via a hostname or an IP address.</t>
              <t>Devices that support loading bootstrapping information from the Internet
              (see <xref target="sources"/>) SHOULD be manufactured with a list of trust anchor
              certificates that can be used to authenticate the Bootstrap Server 
              connections with.</t> 
              <t>Devices that support loading owner signed data (see <xref target="terminology"/>)
              MUST be manufactured with the trust anchor certificate for the Owner Certificates
              that the Manufacturer provides to prospective owners when they enroll in the
              Manufacturer's Zero Touch program (see <xref target="onboarding-and-ordering"/>).</t>
              <t>Devices that support loading owner signed data (see <xref target="terminology"/>)
              MUST also be manufactured with the trust anchor certificate for the device
              Ownership Vouchers that the Manufacturer provides to prospective owners when
              it ships out an order of Zero Touch devices (see <xref target="onboarding-and-ordering"/>).</t>
              <t>Devices MUST be manufactured with an initial
              device identifier (IDevID), as defined in <xref target="Std-802.1AR-2009"/>.
              The IDevID is an X.509 certificate, encoding a globally unique device
              identifier (e.g., serial number).  The device MUST also possess any
              intermediate certificates between the IDevID certificate and the Manufacturer's
              IDevID trust anchor certificate.</t>
              <t>Device MUST be manufactured with a private key that corresponds to the
              public key encoded in the device's IDevID certificate.  This private key SHOULD be
              securely stored, ideally by a cryptographic processor (e.g., a TPM).</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Boot Sequence" anchor="dev-boot-seq">
          <t>A device claiming to support Zero Touch MUST support the boot sequence described in
          this section.</t>
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
    Power On
        |
        v                        No
 1. Running default config?   -------->  Boot normally
        |
        | Yes
        v 
 2. For each supported source for bootstrapping information,
    try to load bootstrapping data from the source
        |
        |
        v                               Yes
 3. Able to bootstrap off any source?  -----> Run with new configuration
        |
        | No
        v
 4. Loop or wait for manual provisioning.

]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>These interactions are described next.
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>When the device powers on, it first checks to see if
              it is running the factory default configuration.  If it is
              running a modified configuration, then it boots normally.</t>
              <t>The device iterates over its list of sources for bootstrapping
              information.  Details for handling different types of sources
              are provided in subsequent sections.</t>
              <t>If the device is able to bootstrap itself off any of 
              the sources for bootstrapping information, it runs with the new
              bootstrapped configuration merged into its running datastore.</t>
              <t>Otherwise the device MAY loop back through the list of
              bootstrapping sources again or wait for manual provisioning.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>When the source is a removable storage device, the device MUST be
          able to read from it signed data (see term) and validate that the
          data was signed by its rightful owner, using the algorithm in
          <xref target="validating-signed-data"/>.</t>

          <t>When the source is a DHCP server, the device MUST be
          able to read from it signed data (see term) and validate that the
          data was signed by its rightful owner, using the algorithm in
          <xref target="validating-signed-data"/>.</t>

          <t>When the source is a bootstrap server, that is, using the RESTCONF
          API presented in <xref target="yang-module"/>, the device MUST be
          able to authenticate the server using one of the the device's preconfigured
          trust anchors.  Once done authenticating the bootstrap server, the device MUST 
          attempt to fetch the bootstrapping data hosted for it there, using
          its unique identifier (e.g., serial number) as the key into the
          "device" list.  If bootstrapping data is found and it is signed,
          then the device MUST first validate that the data was signed by its
          rightful owner using the algorithm in <xref target="validating-signed-data"/>.
          The device then processes the bootstrapping data as described in
          <xref target="processing-bootstrap-data"/>.  The device MAY post 
          progress notification messages to the server, but SHOULD only do
          so if it has first authenticated itself to the server (e.g., client
          authentication).</t>
        </section>  <!-- end boot sequence -->

        <section title="Validating Signed Data" anchor="validating-signed-data">
          <t>If the device is ever presented signed data, it MUST validate the
          signed data as described in this section.</t>
          <t>Whenever there is signed data, the device MUST also be provided
          an Ownership Voucher and an Owner Certificate.</t>
          <t>The device MUST first authenticate the Ownership Voucher by validating
          the signature on it to one of its preconfigured trust anchors (see
          <xref target="factory-defaults"/>) and verify that the voucher contains
          the device's unique identifier (e.g., serial number).  If the
          authentication of the voucher is successful, the device extracts the
          Rightful Owner's identity from the voucher for use in the next step.</t>
          <t>Next the device MUST authenticate the Owner Certificate by performing
          X.509 certificate path validation on it to one of its preconfigured trust
          anchors (see <xref target="factory-defaults"/>) and by verifying that the
          Subject contained in the certificate matches the Rightful Owner identity
          extracted from the voucher in the previous step.  If the authentication
          of the certificate is successful, the device extracts the Owner's public
          key from the certificate for use in the next step.</t>
          <t>Finally the device MUST authenticate the signed data by verifying the
          signature on it was generated by the private key matching the public
          key extracted from the Owner Certificate in the previous step.</t>
          <t>If any of these steps fail, then the device MUST mark the data as
          invalid and not perform any of the subsequent steps.</t>
        </section>  <!-- end validating signed data -->

        <section title="Processing Bootstrap Data" anchor="processing-bootstrap-data">
          <t>In order to process bootstrapping data, the device MUST follow the
          steps presented in this section.</t>
          <t>If the data is redirect-information (see <xref target="information-types"/>),
          the device MUST immediately attempt to establish a RESTCONF connection
          to the provided bootstrap server IP address or hostname.  If a hostname is
          provided and DNS resolves it to more than one IP address, the device MUST
          attempt to try to connect to all of them, until it is able to successfully
          bootstrap off one of them.  The device MUST authenticate the bootstrap server's
          TLS certificate using the X.509 certificate provided by the redirect information.</t>
          <t>If the data is bootstrap-information (see <xref target="information-types"/>),
          the device MUST first check if it contains any boot-image information and, if
          so, check to see if it differs from what the device is currently running and,
          if so, install the boot-image using the provided URI and reboot (Note, it is
          assumed that the boot-image contains an embedded signature that the installation
          step will verify).  This will cause the device's
          bootstrap logic to restart, which will again come to this point, though
          with a matching boot-image, thus letting the device to proceed past this step.
          Next the device MUST process the configuration contained in the bootstrapping
          information, by merging it into its running configuration.</t>
          <t>At this point, the device has completely processed the bootstrapping
          data and is "bootstrap complete".  If the configuration configured the
          device it initiate a call home connection, it would proceed to do so now.
          Otherwise, the device would wait for a NETCONF or RESTCONF client to connect
          to it.</t>
        </section>  <!-- end processing bootstrap data -->

<!--
        <section title="Conformance">
          <t>In order for a device to claim it supports the zero touch solution presented in this document,
          it MUST support loading bootstrap information from an Internet-based bootstrap server using
          the RESTCONF API described by the YANG module in <xref target="yang-module"/>.</t>
        </section> 
--> <!-- end conformance -->

      </section>  <!-- end device details -->

      <section title="YANG-defined API and Artifacts" anchor="api-and-artifacts">
        <t>Central to the solution presented in this document is the use of a YANG module
        <xref target="RFC6020"/> to simultaneously define a RESTCONF based API for a bootstrap/redirect
        server as well as the encoding for signed artifacts that can be conveyed outside of the RESTCONF
        protocol (DHCP, FTP, TFTP, etc.).</t>
        <section title="Module Overview">
          <t>The following tree diagram <xref target="tree-diagram"/> provides an overview for both the
          API and artifacts that can be used outside of RESTCONF.</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ietf-zerotouch-bootstrap-server-tree.txt)
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>In the above diagram, notice that all of the protocol accessible node are read-only,
          to assert that devices can only pull data from the bootstrap server.</t>
          <t>Also notice that the module defines an action statement, which devices may use to provide
          progress notifications to the Bootstrap Server.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="API Examples" anchor="api-examples">
  
          <t>This section presents some examples illustrating device interactions with a Bootstrap
          Server to access Redirect and Bootstrap information, both unsigned and signed, as well
          as to send a progress notification.</t>

          <section title="Unsigned Redirect Information">
  
            <t>The following example illustrates a device using the API to fetch its
            bootstrapping data.  In this example, the device receives unsigned
            redirect information.  This example is representative of a response a well-known
            Internet facing redirect service might return.</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST
-------
GET https://example.com/restconf/data/ietf-zerotouch-bootstrap-server::devices/device=123456 HTTP/1.1
HOST: example.com
Accept: application/yang.data+xml


RESPONSE
--------
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Date: Sat, 31 Oct 2015 17:02:40 GMT
Server: example-server
Content-Type: application/yang.data+xml

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-api-redirect-information-unsigned.xml)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
  
          </section>
  
          <section title="Signed Redirect Information">
  
            <t>The following example illustrates a device using the API to fetch its
            bootstrapping data.  In this example, the device receives signed
            redirect information.  This example is representative of a response
            that redirect service might return if concerned the device might not
            be able to authenticate its TLS certificate.</t>
            <figure>
             <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST
-------
GET https://example.com/restconf/data/ietf-zerotouch-bootstrap-server::devices/device=123456 HTTP/1.1
HOST: example.com
Accept: application/yang.data+xml


RESPONSE
--------
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Date: Sat, 31 Oct 2015 17:02:40 GMT
Server: example-server
Content-Type: application/yang.data+xml


INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-api-redirect-information-signed.xml)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
  
          </section>
  
          <section title="Unsigned Bootstrap Information">
 
            <t>The following example illustrates a device using the API to fetch its
            bootstrapping data.  In this example, the device receives unsigned
            bootstrapping information.  This example is representative of a response
            a locally deployed bootstrap server might return.</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST
-------
GET https://example.com/restconf/data/ietf-zerotouch-bootstrap-server::devices/device=123456 HTTP/1.1
HOST: example.com
Accept: application/yang.data+xml


RESPONSE
--------
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Date: Sat, 31 Oct 2015 17:02:40 GMT
Server: example-server
Content-Type: application/yang.data+xml


INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-api-bootstrap-information-unsigned.xml)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
  
          </section>
  
          <section title="Signed Bootstrap Information">
  
            <t>The following example illustrates a device using the API to fetch its
            bootstrapping data.  In this example, the device receives signed
            bootstrapping information.  This example is representative of a response
            that bootstrap service might return if concerned the device might not
            be able to authenticate its TLS certificate.</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST
-------
GET https://example.com/restconf/data/ietf-zerotouch-bootstrap-server::devices/device=123456 HTTP/1.1
HOST: example.com
Accept: application/yang.data+xml


RESPONSE
--------
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Date: Sat, 31 Oct 2015 17:02:40 GMT
Server: example-server
Content-Type: application/yang.data+xml

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-api-bootstrap-information-signed.xml)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
  
          </section>

          <section title="Progress Notifications">
            <t>The following example illustrates a device using the API to post
            a notification to the server.  The device may send more than one
            notification to the server (e.g., to provide status updates).  The
            YANG module defines only one notification type, bootstrap-complete.
            Other notification types may be defined through YANG augmentation.</t>

            <t>The bootstrap server MUST NOT process a notification from a
            device without first authenticating the device.  This is in contrast
            to when a device is fetching data from the server, a read-only
            operation, in which case device authentication is not strictly
            required.</t>

            <t>In this example, the device sends a notification indicating that
            it has completed bootstrapping off the data provided by the server.
            This example also illustrates the device sending its SSH host keys
            to the bootstrap server, which it might, for example, forward onto
            a downstream NMS component, so that it can subsequently authenticate
            the device when establishing a NETCONF over SSH connection to it.</t>

            <t>A device providing its SSH host key or TLS server certificate is
            not needed when the device has an IDevID certificate
            <xref target="Std-802.1AR-2009"/> and is able to present the IDevID
            certificate as its SSH host key or TLS server certificate, when
            establishing a NETCONF or RESTCONF connection.</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST
-------
POST https://example.com/restconf/data/ietf-zerotouch-bootstrap-server::devices/device=123456/notification HTTP/1.1
HOST: example.com
Content-Type: application/yang.data+xml

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-api-bootstrap-notification.xml)


RESPONSE
--------
HTTP/1.1 204 No Content
Date: Sat, 31 Oct 2015 17:02:40 GMT
Server: example-server
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
 
          </section>

        </section> <!-- API Examples -->

        <section title="Artifact Examples" anchor="artifact-examples">

          <t>This section presents some examples for how the same information provided by the
          API can be packaged into stand alone artifacts.  The encoding for these artifacts is
          the same as if an HTTP GET request had been sent to the RESTCONF URL for the specific
          resource.</t>

          <t>Encoding these artifacts for use outside of the RESTCONF protocol extends their
          utility for other deployment scenarios, such as when a local DHCP server or a
          removable storage device is used.  By way of example, this may be done to address an
          inability for the device to access an Internet facing bootstrap/redirect server, or
          just for a preference to use locally deployed infrastructure.</t>

          <section title="Signed Redirect Information">
            <t>The following example illustrates how a redirect can be encoded into an artifact
            for use outside of the RESTCONF protocol.  The redirect information is signed so
            that it is secure even when no transport-level security is provided.</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-file-redirect-information.xml)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>

          <section title="Signed Bootstrap Information">
            <t>The following example illustrates how bootstrapping data can be encoded into an artifact
            for use outside of the RESTCONF protocol.  The bootstrapping information is signed so
            that it is secure when no transport-level security is provided.</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-file-bootstrap-information.xml)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>

          <section title="Owner Certificate" anchor="ex-owner-certificate">
            <t>The following example illustrates how the owner certificate, along with its CRL, can be
            encoded into an artifact for use outside of the RESTCONF protocol.  As the Owner Certificate
            and CRL are already signed by the manufacturer, an additional owner signature is unnecessary.</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-file-owner-certificate.xml)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>

          <section title="Ownership Voucher" anchor="ex-ownership-voucher">
            <t>The following example illustrates how the ownership voucher, along with its CRL, can be
            encoded into an artifact for use outside of the RESTCONF protocol.  As the Ownership Voucher
            and CRL are already signed by the manufacturer, an additional owner signature is unnecessary.</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-file-ownership-voucher.xml)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>

        </section> <!-- Artifact Examples -->

        <section title="YANG Module" anchor="yang-module">
          <t>The bootstrap server's device-facing interface is normatively defined
          by the following YANG module:</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-zerotouch-bootstrap-server@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(ietf-zerotouch-bootstrap-server@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>

]]></artwork>
          </figure>

        </section>
      </section>


      <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-con">

        <section title="Immutable storage for trust anchors">
          <t>Devices MUST ensure that all their trust anchor 
          certificates, including those for the Owner Certificate 
          and Ownership Voucher, are protected from
          external modification.</t>
          <t>It may be necessary to update these 
          certificates over time (e.g., the manufacturer wants to
          delegate trust to a new CA).  It is therefore expected
          that devices MAY update these trust anchors when 
          needed through a verifiable process, such as a 
          software upgrade using signed software images.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Real time clock">
          <t>The solution for signed data includes validating
          Owner Certificates and Ownership Vouchers, each of which
          may contain expirations.  Further, the solution includes
          using a CRLs, which also require freshness.  Device
          implementations should take care to ensure the devices
          have a reliable clock when processing signed data.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Entropy loss over time">
          <t>Section 7.2.7.2 of the IEEE Std 802.1AR-2009 standard says
          that IDevID certificate should never expire (i.e. having a
          notAfter 99991231235959Z).  Given the long-lived
          nature of these certificates, it is paramount to use a 
          strong key length (e.g., 512-bit ECC).   Manufacturers SHOULD
          deploy Online Certificate State Protocol (OCSP) responders 
          or CRL Distribution Points (CDP) to revoke certificates in 
          case necessary.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Serial Numbers">
          <t>This draft suggests using the device's serial number as
          the unique identifier in its IDevID certificate.  This is 
          because serial numbers are ubiquitous and prominently 
          contained in invoices and on labels affixed to devices and
          their packaging.  That said, serial numbers many times encode
          revealing information, such as the device's model number,
          manufacture date, and/or sequence number.  Knowledge of this
          information may provide an adversary with details needed 
          to launch an attack.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-considerations">
        <t>Editor Note: this section needs to be rewritten to use the
        redirect and bootstrap information types (see <xref target="information-types"/>).</t>
        <section title="Zero Touch Information DHCP Options" anchor="zerotouch-info-option">
          <t>The following registrations are in accordance to RFC 2939 for
          "BOOTP Manufacturer Extensions and DHCP Options" registry maintained at
          http://www.iana.org/assignments/bootp-dhcp-parameters.</t>
          <section title="DHCP v4 Option">
            <figure>
              <artwork>
   Tag: XXX

   Name: Zero Touch Information

   Description: Returns a list of null-terminated Configuration 
                Server hostnames and/or IP addresses.

    Code   Len
   +-----+-----+------+------+----
   | XXX |  n  | svr1 | svr2 | ...
   +-----+-----+------+------+----

   Reference: RFC XXXX
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>
          <section title="DHCP v6 Option">
            <figure>
              <artwork>
   Tag: YYY

   Name: Zero Touch Information

   Description: Returns a list of null-terminated Configuration 
                Server hostnames and/or IP addresses.

    Code   Len
   +-----+-----+------+------+----
   | YYY |  n  | svr1 | svr2 | ...
   +-----+-----+------+------+----

   Reference: RFC XXXX
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Acknowledgements">
        <t>The authors would like to thank for following for
        lively discussions on list and in the halls (ordered
        by last name): 
        David Harrington,
        Dean Bogdanovic,
        Martin Bjorklund,
        Max Pritikin,
        Stephen Hanna,
        Wes Hardaker,
        Russ Mundy,
        Reinaldo Penno,
        Randy Presuhn,
        Juergen Schoenwaelder.</t>
          
        <t>Special thanks goes to Steve Hanna, Russ Mundy, and 
        Wes Hardaker for brainstorming the original I-D's solution 
        during the IETF 87 meeting in Berlin.</t>
      </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            &rfc2119;
            &rfc6020;

            <reference anchor="Std-802.1AR-2009" target="http://standards.ieee.org/findstds/standard/802.1AR-2009.html">
                <front>
                    <title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks - Secure Device Identity</title>
                    <author fullname="WG802.1 - Higher Layer LAN Protocols Working Group">
                        <organization>IEEE SA-Standards Board</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="December" year="2009"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="draft-ietf-netconf-call-home" target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-netconf-call-home-04">
                <front>
                    <title>NETCONF Call Home (work in progress)</title>
                    <author initials="K.W." surname="Watsen"
                            fullname="Kent Watsen">
                        <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="October" year="2014"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="draft-ietf-netconf-server-model" target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-netconf-server-model-06">
                <front>
                    <title>NETCONF Server Model (work in progress)</title>
                    <author initials="K.W." surname="Watsen"
                            fullname="Kent Watsen">
                        <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="September" year="2014"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
         <reference anchor='draft-ietf-netconf-restconf' target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-netconf-restconf-04">
           <front>
             <title>RESTCONF Protocol</title>
             <author initials='A.B.' surname='Bierman'
                fullname='Andy Bierman'>
               <organization>YumaWorks</organization>
             </author>
             <author initials='M' surname='Bjorklund'
                fullname='Martin Bjorklund'>
               <organization>Tail-f Systems</organization>
             </author>
             <author initials='K.W.' surname='Watsen'
                fullname='Kent Watsen'>
               <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
             </author>
             <date year='2014' />
           </front>
           <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft'
                  value='draft-ieft-netconf-restconf-04' />
        </reference>

        </references>

        <references title="Informative References">

            &rfc6241;
            &rfc7317;

<!--
          <reference anchor='draft-pritikin-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra' target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-pritikin-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra">
            <front>
              <title>Bootstrapping Key Infrastructures</title>
              <author initials='M.P.' surname='Pritikin'
                 fullname='Max Pritikin'>
                <organization>Cisco</organization>
              </author>
              <author initials='M.B.' surname='Behringer'
                 fullname='Micheal Behringer'>
                <organization>Cisco</organization>
              </author>
              <author initials='S.B.' surname='Bjarnason'
                 fullname='Steinthor Bjarnason'>
                <organization>Cisco</organization>
              </author>
              <date year='2015' />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft'
                   value='draft-pritikin-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra-01' />
          </reference>
-->

        </references>

        <section title="Examples" anchor="examples">
          <section title="Ownership Voucher" anchor="ex-owner-voucher">

            <t>Following describes an example data-model for an Ownership 
            Voucher.  Real vouchers are expected to be encoded in a 
            Manufacturer-specific format outside the of scope for this draft.</t>

            <t>A tree diagram describing an Ownership Voucher:</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ietf-zerotouch-ownership-voucher-tree.txt)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>The YANG module for this example voucher:</t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-zerotouch-ownership-voucher@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(ietf-zerotouch-ownership-voucher@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>

]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Change Log">
          <section title="ID to 00">
            <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Major structural update; the essence is the same.
              Most every section was rewritten to some degree.</t>
              <t>Added a Use Cases section</t>
              <t>Added diagrams for "Actors and Roles" and
              "NMS Precondition" sections, and greatly improved
              the "Device Boot Sequence" diagram</t>
              <t>Removed support for physical presence or any
              ability for Configlets to not be signed.</t>
              <t>Defined the Zero Touch Information DHCP option</t>
              <t>Added an ability for devices to also download
              images from Configuration Servers</t>
              <t>Added an ability for Configlets to be encrypted</t>
              <t>Now Configuration Servers only have to support
              HTTP/S - no other schemes possible</t>
            </list>
            </t>
          </section>
          <section title="00 to 01">
            <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Added boot-image and validate-owner annotations
                 to the "Actors and Roles" diagram.</t>
              <t>Fixed 2nd paragraph in section 7.1 to reflect 
                 current use of anyxml.</t>
              <t>Added encrypted and signed-encrypted examples</t>
              <t>Replaced YANG module with XSD schema</t>
              <t>Added IANA request for the Zero Touch Information DHCP Option</t>
              <t>Added IANA request for media types for boot-image and configuration</t>
            </list>
            </t>
          </section>
          <section title="01 to 02">
            <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Replaced the need for a Configuration Signer with the
              ability for each NMS to be able to sign its own configurations,
              using Manufacturer signed Ownership Vouchers and Owner certificates.</t>
              <t>Renamed Configuration Server to Bootstrap Server, a more
              representative name given the information devices download from it.</t>
              <t>Replaced the concept of a Configlet by defining a southbound 
              interface for the Bootstrap Server using YANG.</t>
              <t>Removed the IANA request for the boot-image and configuration
              media types</t>
            </list>
            </t>
          </section>
          <section title="02 to 03">
            <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Minor update, mostly just to add an Editor's Note to show how this
              draft might integrate with the draft-pritikin-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra.</t>
            </list>
            </t>
          </section>
          <section title="03 to 04">
            <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Major update formally introducing unsigned data and support for
              Internet-based redirect servers.</t>
              <t>Added many terms to Terminology section.</t>
              <t>Added all new "Guiding Principles" section.</t>
              <t>Added all new "Sources for Bootstrapping Data" section.</t>
              <t>Rewrote the "Interactions" section and renamed it "Workflow Overview".</t>
            </list>
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>

