<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6187 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6187.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7317 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7317.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<!--<?rfc strict="no"?> -->

<rfc category="std"
     ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-ietf-netconf-zerotouch-latest">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="ZeroTouch">Zero Touch Provisioning for NETCONF Call Home (ZeroTouch)</title>
        <author initials="K.W." surname="Watsen" fullname="Kent Watsen">
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <email>kwatsen@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="S.H." surname="Hanna" fullname="Stephen Hanna">
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <email>shanna@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="J.M.C." surname="Clarke" fullname="Joe Marcus Clarke">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <email>jclarke@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="M.A." surname="Abrahamsson" fullname="Mikael Abrahamsson">
            <organization>T-Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <email>"mikael.abrahamsson@t-systems.se</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date day="27" month="October" year="2014"/>
        <area>Operations</area>
        <workgroup>NETCONF Working Group</workgroup>
        <keyword>zerotouch</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>This draft presents a technique for establishing a
            secure NETCONF connection between a newly deployed 
            IP-based device, configured with just its factory 
            default settings, and the new owner's Network Management 
            System (NMS).</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
      <section title="Introduction">

        <section title="Terminology">
          <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
          and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Objectives">
          <t>A fundamental business requirement is to reduce 
          operational costs where possible.  Deploying new 
          IP-based devices is many times one of the largest
          costs in running a network, as sending trained 
          specialists to each site to do an installation is 
          both cost prohibitive and does not scale.</t>
          <t>Both networking vendors and standard bodies have
          tried to address this issue, with varying levels of
          success.  For instance, the Broadband Forum TR-069 
          specification <xref target="TR069"/> relies solely
          on DHCP for NMS discovery, but this can only work in
          environments where the DHCP server is locally administered,
          which is not the case when the device is connected to 
          an ISP's network.  In another example, some network
          vendors have enabled their devices to load an initial
          configuration from removable storage media (e.g., a
          USB flash drive), but not all devices have such ports.</t>
          <t>The solution presented herein, ZeroTouch, enables
          a device to securely obtain an initial configuration
          from the network without any operator intervention.
          The discovered configuration initiates the device to
          "call home" using either SSH or TLS, as described in 
          <xref target="NETCONF-CALL-HOME"/>.</t>
          <t><vspace blankLines="3"/></t>
        </section>


        <section title="Use Cases" anchor="use-cases">
          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Connecting to a remotely administered network
                <list style="empty">
                  <t>This use-case involves scenarios, such as a remote
                  branch office or convenience store, whereby the device
                  connects to an ISP's network.  In this case, the device
                  receives only generic networking settings (address, netmask,
                  gateway, DNS servers, etc.) provided by the ISP,
                  with no site-specific customizations, such that the
                  device has no recourse but to reach out to the 
                  presumably insecure network for its initial 
                  configuration.</t>
                </list>
              </t>
              <t>Connecting to a locally administered network
                <list style="empty">
                  <t>This use-case covers all other scenarios and 
                  differs only in that the device may additionally
                  receive some site-specific information to guide
                  its call home process, which could then direct
                  it to a local server for its initial configuration.
                  If no site-specific information is provided, or the
                  device is unable to use the information provided,
                  it can then reach out to network just as it would
                  for a remotely administered network.</t>
                </list>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t><vspace blankLines="30"/></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Actors and Roles">
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                               fetches Configlet and
                 +----------+  boot-image, if needed
    +------------|  Device  |---------------------+
    |            +----------+                     |
    |                 ^                           |
    |                 |                           V
    | call home       | manufactures         +----------+
    |                 | with necessary       |  Config  |
    |                 | default state        |  Server  |<----+
    |                 | for ZeroTouch        +----------+     |
    |                 |                                       |
    |                 |                                       |
    |            +----------+  delegates trust                |
    |            |  Vendor  |-------------------+             |
    |            +----------+                   |             |
    |               ^    ^                      |             |
    |               |    |                      V             |
    |               |    |                 +----------+       |
    |       imports |    | validate owner  |  Config  |       |
    |         trust |    +-----------------|  Signer  |       |
    |        anchor |                      +----------+       |
    |               |                           ^             |
    |               |                           |             |
    |            +---------+  requests signing  |             |
    +----------->|   NMS   |--------------------+             |
                 +---------+                                  |
                     |                                        |
                     +----------------------------------------+
                       signed Configlet and boot-image file
]]></artwork>

              <postamble>Though not represented as a box in the diagram,
              the Configlet is also a first-class object in the solution.</postamble>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Configlet
              <list style="empty">
                <t>A Configlet is an XML document that, when
                loaded onto a device, configures the device
                to initiate a call home connection to a deployment
                specific NMS, as well as set a local administrator
                account for the NMS to log into.  The Configlet
                is signed and optionally encrypted.  More information
                about Configlets is in <xref target="configlet"/>.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Configuration Server
              <list style="empty">
                <t>A Configuration Server hosts Configlets and 
                boot-images to be downloaded over a network via
                HTTP/S.  Configuration Servers can be deployed 
                either on the locally
                administered network or on some external network
                (e.g., the Internet).  Configuration Servers are
                known to devices in the form of a URI, which can
                be either preconfigured or dynamically discovered.
                More information about Configuration Servers is 
                in <xref target="config-server"/>.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Configuration Signer
              <list style="empty">
                <t>A Configuration Signer is an entity that the
                device's vendor has delegated the Configlet-signing
                function to.  A Configuration Signer only needs to 
                ensure that the requestor is the rightful owner of 
                the device to which a configuration is destined.  A
                Configuration Signer may be site-specific or an
                external entity. More information about 
                Configuration Signers is in
                <xref target="config-signer"/>.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Device
              <list style="empty">
                <t>The device is the networking entity that initiates
                ZeroTouch, whenever booting with its factory default
                settings.  The device is preconfigured with a secure
                device identity, Configuration Servers URIs, and
                certificates for both Configuration Signers and 
                Configuration Servers it trusts by default.  A
                device may dynamically discover additional URIs and
                certificates from a locally-administered network.
                More information about Devices
                is in <xref target="device"/>.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Network Management System
              <list style="empty">
                <t>The NMS is the deployment-specific system that
                devices initiate their call home connections to.
                The NMS must be configured with vendor-specific
                trust anchors and unique device identifiers.
                The administrators of the NMS system interact with
                Configuration Signer and Configuration Server
                systems to stage the the device configurations.
                More information about Network Management Systems
                is in <xref target="nms"/>.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Vendor
              <list style="empty">
                <t>Vendors manufacture the devices with secure
                 device identities and preconfigured Configuration
                 URIs, and Configuration Signer certificates.
                 Vendors are the de facto Configuration Signer
                 for the devices it manufactures, but may
                 delegate that role to external Configuration
                 Signers.  More information about Vendors is in
                 <xref target="vendor"/>.</t>
               </list>
            </t>
          </list>
          </t>
          <t><vspace blankLines="3"/></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Configuration Server" anchor="config-server">
        <t>A Configuration Server is the entity hosting configurations
        that can be downloaded over a network. This section describes
        the service interface a Configuration Server MUST implement
        as well as what's needed for transport security.</t>
        <section title="Service Interface" anchor="service-interface">
          <t>Configuration Servers are known to devices in the form
          of a URI.  Configuration Servers MUST support the URI schemes
          "https" and "http".  Other URI schemes are not supported.</t>
          <t>When accessing a Configuration Server, the device
          appends its unique device identifier (UID) to the URI.  The
          unique identifier MUST be the same as the identifier stored
          within the device's IDevID certificate, which is described
          in <xref target="device-precondition"/>.</t>
          <t>
          For instance, if the URI were:
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
      http://example.com/zerotouch/devices/
      https://example.com/zerotouch?id=
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          then the device would try to access:
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
      http://example.com/zerotouch/devices/<uid>
      https://example.com/zerotouch?id=<uid>
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          </t>
          <t>When accessing the Configuration Server, the HTTP
          Accept-Type MUST be set to either "application/zerotouch-configlet"
          or "application/zerotouch-bootimage".  Please see 
          <xref target="zerotouch-media-types"/>. A wildcard Accept-Type
          (e.g., */*) SHOULD default to "application/zerotouch-configlet".</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Interactive Interface">
          <t>The Configuration server SHOULD provide a
          user-facing interface to enable the end-user to
          provide a Configlet and, optionally, a bootimage file.
          How the Configlet and bootimage file are provided to the
          Configuration Server is outside the scope of this
          document.</t>
          <t><vspace blankLines="3"/></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Transport Security">
          <t>As described in <xref target="config-signer"/>, configurations
          MUST be signed and MAY be encrypted.  As such, transport-level
          security is not needed to assure authenticity or confidentiality
          of the configuration itself.  However, transport-level security
          enables devices to authenticate the Configuration Server and
          also extends confidentiality to the application-level protocol.
          Therefore, it is RECOMMENDED that only secure URL schemes are
          used (see <xref target="service-interface"/>).</t>
          <t>If a Configuration Server uses X.509-based encryption, 
          then its X.509 certificate MUST have a chain of trust
          to a trust anchor known to devices (see 
          <xref target="device-precondition"/>.  More specifically, the
          Configuration Server MUST possess all the intermediate 
          certificates leading to the trust anchor.</t>
          <t>When a Configuration Server negotiates encryption with the
          device, it provides the chain of certificates, from its server
          specific certificate to, but not including, its trust anchor.  
          Including the trust anchor's certificate is unnecessary since 
          the device MUST be pre-provisioned with it. Devices need the 
          chain of certificates to be passed so they can validate the server
          using only a simple list of Configuration Server trust anchors.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Expiration Policy">
          <t>An expiration policy is needed to limit how long a 
          Configuration Server needs to retain a configuration and, 
          in turn, how many configurations it might need to retain
          at a given time.</t>
          <t>It is expected that Configuration Servers will enable
          retention information to be given at the same time as
          when the configuration is provided to it.  Options should
          be temporal in nature, not based on access counts, so as
          to thwart a DoS attack whereby the configuration is accessed
          by an entity other than the device.  Configuration Servers
          SHOULD put a limit on the maximum amount of time it will
          hold onto a configuration before purging it, even if the
          configuration had never been accessed.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Troubleshooting and Auditing">
          <t>In order to facilitate troubleshooting and auditing, the
          Configuration Server SHOULD record into a log a record of 
          the various Configlet download requests.  This draft does 
          not define what information should be kept or for how 
          long.</t>
          <t><vspace blankLines="3"/></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Configuration Signer" anchor="config-signer">
        <section title="Overview" anchor="signer-overview">
          <t>A Configuration Signer MUST be able to sign configurations.
          This function requires the Configuration Signer be able to
          authenticate that the requestor is the true owner of the
          device, as identified within the contents of the configuration
          being signed.</t>
          <t>The user interface a Configuration Signer provides to perform
          its role is outside the scope of this document.  However, in
          order to meet operational expectations, the time it takes to
          respond to a request should be as expeditious as possible.</t>
          <t>A Configuration Signer does not need to retain a configuration 
          after signing it.  The Configuration Signer SHOULD retain an
          audit log for indemnification purposes.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Signing Configurations">
           <t>A Configuration Signer MUST have an X.509 certificate with 
           Key Usage capable of signing data (digitalSignature) and 
           be signed by a certificate authority having a chain of 
           trust leading to a trust anchor known to the devices 
           loading its Configlets.  The Configuration Signer MUST 
           possess all intermediate certificates leading to its 
           trust anchor.</t>
           <t>When a Configuration Signer signs a Configlet, it attaches
           both the signature and the chain of X.509 certificates,
           including its own, but not necessarily including the
           trust anchor's certificate.  This chain of certificates
           is needed so a device can validate a Configlet using
           only the Configuration Signer trust anchors known to it.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Optional Encryption">
          <t>A Configuration Signer MAY optionally encrypt configurations
          prior to signing them.  This function requires the Configuration
          Signer know the device's unique public key, as encoded within
          its secure device identity certificate.</t>
          <!-- KENT: what KeyUsage bits need to be set?
                   - are they in IDEVID? -->
        </section>
        <section title="Delegation of Trust" anchor="delegate-trust">
          <t>A device's vendor is the root of trust for all of its
          devices.  That is, the vendor's devices implicitly trust
          the vendor for such things as software images, subscription
          updates, and licenses.  As such, the vendor is the ultimate
          Configuration Signer for its devices.</t>
          <t>However, both vendors and its customers may prefer that
          this role be performed by another entity.  For instance,
          a vendor may not want this role due to it being outside
          its primary business function, and customers may not want
          the vendor to have this role for privacy reasons.</t>
          <t>It is therefore provided that a vendor MAY delegate
          the Configuration Signer role to other entities.  Using
          X.509 certificates, the Vendor need only sign the
          delegate's certificate signing request (CSR), providing
          back to the delegate a signed X.509 certificate
          authenticating its ability to perform the signing
          function.</t>
          <t>In order enable a delegate to fulfill its operational
          role, as described in <xref target="signer-overview"/>,
          the vendor MUST provide a mechanism that can be used to
          authenticate if a given requestor is the true owner of a
          specific device.  Additionally, to support Configuration
          Signers that want to encrypt configurations, the vendor
          MUST also provide a means for the Configuration Signer
          to know the public key for a given device.  How the vendor
          provides this information to Configuration Signers is
          outside the scope of this document.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Delegation to a Specific Customer">
          <t>The general expectation is that the Configuration 
          Signer is an impartial 3rd-party.  However,  certain 
          deployments may want to be able to perform the function for 
          themselves.  Yet without constraints, that deployment
          could sign configurations for devices that do not
          belong to it.</t>
          <t>Resolving this concern is possible when 1) the
          deployment specific Configuration Signer's certificate
          is annotated with a customer identifier and 2) the
          devices sold to that customer have that same identifier
          encoded into their secure device identifier.</t>
          <t>This entails the vendor augmenting its manufacturing
          process for these special devices, which would likely
          be sold directly to the customer, as opposed to through
          a sales channel.  This takes extraordinary effort and
          likely only implemented for the most important customers,
          if at all.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Device" anchor="device">
        <section title="Overview">
          <t>While the wholistic solution, ZeroTouch, involves a
          number of entities, a device being powered-on is the
          essential event that sets things in motion.</t>
          <t>Whenever a device boots with its factory
          default settings, it initiates ZeroTouch with the goal
          of finding a configuration to initialize itself with.
          Once a configuration is found, the device initializes
          its running datastore with it and then enters normal
          operation.  Since the configuration initializes the 
          device to call home upon entering its normal operating
          mode, the device immediately begins trying to establish
          a secure connection with the deployment specific NMS.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Factory Default State" anchor="device-precondition">
          <t>
            <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
  +------------------------------------------------------------------+
  |                            <device>                              |
  |                                                                  |
  |     +------------------------------------------------------+     |
  |     |                <immutable storage>                   |     |
  |     |                                                      |     |
  |     |  list of Configuration Signer trust anchor certs     |     |
  |     |  list of Configuration Server trust anchor certs     |     |
  |     +------------------------------------------------------+     |
  |                                                                  |
  |   +----------------------------------------------------------+   |
  |   |                    <other storage>                       |   |
  |   |                                                          |   |
  |   |  two sets of Configuration Server URIs                   |   |
  |   |  IDevID entity & associated intermediate certificate(s)  |   |
  |   +----------------------------------------------------------+   |
  |                                                                  |
  |                    +----------------------+                      |
  |                    |   <secure storage>   |                      |
  |                    |                      |                      |
  |                    |  IDevID private key  |                      |
  |                    +----------------------+                      |
  |                                                                  |
  +------------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>Devices supporting ZeroTouch  MUST have a 
          manufacturer-provisioned secure device identifier, as 
          defined in <xref target="Std-802.1AR-2009"/>.  This identifier
          is known by the IEEE standard as the Initial Device 
          Identifier (IDevID).  The IDevID includes both an X.509
          certificate, encoding a globally unique per-device
          identifier, and a chain of X.509 certificates leading to the
          manufacturer's well-known trust anchor.  The IDevID is needed
          in order for the NMS to positively authenticate a device.
          The IDevID certificate MUST be used by the NETCONF server
          as its SSH host-key (see <xref target="RFC6187"/>) or its TLS
          server certificate, depending on which protocol is used.</t>
          <t>Devices supporting ZeroTouch MUST be pre-provisioned with
          one or more URIs for Internet-based Configuration Servers.
          These URIs SHOULD be partitioned into one set that contains
          secure schemes (e.g. https://) and another set that
          contains insecure schemes (e.g., http://).  The
          reason for partitioning the URIs is so all the secure schemes
          can attempted before any of the insecure schemes (see
          <xref target="dev-boot-seq"/>).  When using a secure scheme,
          the Configuration Server MUST be authenticated using a
          trust anchor the device possesses.  As each Configuration 
          Server may use a different trust anchor, this generalizes 
          to a list of Configuration Server trust anchor certificates.</t>
          <t>In order to verify the signature on retrieved 
          configurations, devices supporting ZeroTouch MUST also
          possess the trust anchor for the Configuration Signer
          that signed the configuration.  Generally, only the 
          manufacturer's trust anchor is needed, as it can then
          delegate trust for 3rd-party Configuration Signers
          (see <xref target="delegate-trust"/>).  However, for
          various reasons, there may be a need for more than one
          root anchor and therefore this generalizes to a list
          of Configuration Signer trust anchor certificates.</t>
          <t>Devices SHOULD ensure that the certificates for its 
          trust anchors are protected from external modification.
          It is for this reason that the diagram shows the 
          Configuration Signer and Configuration Server certificates 
          in immutable storage.  Similarly, per <xref target="Std-802.1AR-2009"/>,
          the IDevID private key shall be stored confidentially and
          not available outside the IDevID module, hence the diagram
          shows it is held within secure storage.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Boot Sequence" anchor="dev-boot-seq">
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
    DEVICE           DHCP                         CONFIGURATION         NMS
      |          SERVER/RELAY                        SERVERS             |
      |                |                                |                |
  +-->|                |                                |                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |--[1. if running config != factory default, boot normally]--+     |
  |   |                |                                |          |     |
<------------------------------------------------------------------+     |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |--(2. discovery)-->| [3. if no dhcp server found, boot normally]  |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |  +--(4. offer)-|                                |                |
  |   |  |             |                                |                |
  |   |  +--[5. add any listed config servers to built-in list]--+       |
  |   |                |                                |        |       |
  |   |<---------------------------------------------------------+       |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   | (6. iterate until match, else boot normally)    |                |
  |   |------------------------------------------------>|                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |<---------------------------(zerotouch info)-----|                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |--[7. if current image != expected, get image]-->|                |
  |   |                |                                |                |
  |   |  +-------------------------------------(image)--|                |
  |   |  |             |                                |                |
  |   |  +--[8. if image valid, install & reboot]--+    |                |
  |   |                |                           |    |                |
  +------------------------------------------------+    |                |
      |                |                                |                |
      |                |                                |                |
      |                |                                |                |
      |--[9. get config]------------------------------->|                |
      |                |                                |                |
      |  +------------------------------------(config)--|                |
      |  |             |                                |                |
      |  +--[10. merge configuration into running]----+ |                | 
      |                |                              | |                |
      |     +-----------------------------------------+ |                |
      |     |          |                                |                |
      |     +--[11. per new configuration, call home]------------------->|
      |                |                                |                |
      |                |                                |                |
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style="format (%d)">
                 <t>Whenever a device boots with its factory default settings,
                      it initiates ZeroTouch with the goal of finding a
                      configuation that will enable it to call home to its
                      deployment-specific NMS.  Else, if the configuration
                      has been changed from the factory default, it will
                      boot normally.
                 </t>
                 <t>The discovery process begins with the device using the
                      DHCP protocol to obtain a dynamic assignment for its
                      networking stack.  When broadcasting the DISCOVERY
                      request, the device may provide any DHCP options to
                      identify itself or the type of device it is
                      (e.g. DHCPv4 options 60 or 61).
                 </t>
                 <t>If the no DHCP offer is received, then the device will
                      continue to boot normally.
                 </t>
                 <t>If the DHCP servers reside on a locally administered
                      network (see <xref target="use-cases"/>), then their
                      OFFER responses MAY include the ZeroTouch Information
                      DHCP option defined in <xref target="zerotouch-info-option"/>,
                      as well as the legacy vendor specific information (e.g.
                      DHCPv4 options 43, 66, and 67).  If a DHCP server provides both
                      ZeroTouch Information and the vendor specific information DHCP
                      options, then the ZeroTouch information option MUST be processed 
                      first.
                 </t>
                 <t>The ZeroTouch Information option <xref target="zero-touch-info-option"/>
                      provides a set of Configuration Server URIs.  If returned by the DHCP
                      server, the device MUST append each URI to the end of one of its two
                      sets of Configuration Server URIs, depending on if the URI's scheme
                      is secure or not.  URIs added this way MUST remain distinguishable
                      from those URIs with which the device shipped for reasons discussed next.
                 </t>
                 <!--
                 <t>Before trying any of the Configuration Server URIs,
                      the device SHOULD first try to load a configuration
                      through local means that assert physical presence.
                      For instance, a removable USB flash drive or 
                      near-field communication mechanism.  Configurations 
                      obtained through an assertion of physical presence 
                      do not have to be signed or contain the device's
                      unique identifier (e.g., serial number).  If a 
                      Configlet is found, the device MUST use it without
                      trying any of the Configuration Server URIs.</t>
                 -->
                 <t>The device then iterates over its two sets of Configuration
                      Server URIs.  The device MUST first try all of the URIs from
                      the set having secure schemes before trying any of the URIs
                      from the set having insecure schemes.  For each URI, until a
                      match is found and successfully loaded, the device attempts to
                      initialize itself from the URI.  If the URI uses a secure scheme
                      (e.g. https), the device MUST validate the Configuration Server's
                      certificate using one of its Configuration Server trust anchors.
                      If the device is unable to verify the server's certificate, the
                      device MUST skip that URI.  If the device reaches the end of all
                      its URIs without finding a usable match, it SHOULD continue its
                      normal boot sequence using its factory default configuration.
                      <vspace/>
                      When the device is accessing a Configuration Server URI with
                      which it was shipped (i.e. not discovered while initializing
                      its networking), it MUST do so by appending its UID to the
                      URI string and using the Accept-Type "application/zerotouch-configlet",
                      as described in <xref target="config-server"/>.  For URIs discovered
                      via the ZeroTouch Information option, the device MAY also try
                      the raw URI after trying the permutation using its UID.
                      <vspace/>
                      If the Configuration Server returns a configuration, the device
                      MUST first verify it before use.  Configuration verification entails
                      both verifying the configuration's signature using the device's list
                      of Configuration Signer trust anchors, and also verifying that the
                      unique identifier within the Configlet [JC: Should this be configuration?] matches the device's
                      unique identifier.
                 </t>
                 <t>Once the configuration is authenticated, the device MUST compare
                      its software image version with the expected version specified
                      within the configuration.  If there is a mismatch, the device MUST
                      download the correct image version from the Configuration Server
                      by appending its UID to the Configuration Server's URI string
                      and using the Accept-Type "application/zerotouch-bootimage", as
                      described in <xref target="config-server"/>.  For URIs discovered
                      via the ZeroTouch Information option, the device MAY also try the
                      raw URI after first trying the permutation using its UID.
                 </t>
                 <t>Once the image has been downloaded, the device MUST first validate
                      the image integrity, and if valid [JC: How?  Out of scope, but what
                      should we say here?] install it and reboot,
                      still with the factory default settings configured, so that ZeroTouch
                      restarts when the device comes back up.
                 </t>
                 <t>When the device is running the correct software image version, it moves
                      on to the configuration contents of the Configlet obtained in step 6.
                 </t>
                 <t>The device merges the Configlet's [JC: should this be configuration?] contents into
                      its running configuration.  This step effectively modifies the
                      device so that it is no longer having its factory default
                      configuration.  Thus, at this point, a reboot is no longer
                      expected to start the ZeroTouch process.
                 </t>
                 <t>Though not technically required, the Configlet is presumed to have
                      configured the device to "call home."  As soon as this
                      configuration is merged into the running configuration, the
                      device SHOULD immediately begin trying to establish the call
                      home connection as specified by the Configlet.
                      <vspace/>
                      If configured to establish a SSH connection, the device MUST
                      use its IDevID and associated intermediate X.509 certificates
                      as its host key per RFC 6187 <xref target="RFC6187"/>.  If
                      configured to establish a TLS connection, the device MUST use its
                      IDevID and associated intermediate X.509 certificates as its
                      server-side certificate for the TLS connection.
                 </t>
            </list>
            <t>In order to facilitate troubleshooting, the device SHOULD
                 record into a log information relating to its stepping through
                 the ZeroTouch sequence.  This draft does not define any specific
                 log messages, for instance, for Syslog or SNMP.
            </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Network Management System (NMS)" anchor="nms">
        <section title="Overview">
          <t>The NMS is the ultimate destination of ZeroTouch for 
          a device.   It is the NMS's network address configured 
          in the Configlet.  The device will initiate a call home
          connection to the NMS, using either SSH or TLS, as 
          configured by the Configlet loaded.</t>
          <t><vspace blankLines="30"/></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Precondition">
          <t>
            <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
  +------------------------------------------------------------------+
  |                              <nms>                               |
  |                                                                  |
  |     +------------------------------------------------------+     |
  |     |                <immutable storage>                   |     |
  |     |                                                      |     |
  |     |  list of IDevID trust anchor certificates            |     |
  |     |  list of expected device unique identifiers          |     |
  |     +------------------------------------------------------+     |
  |                                                                  |
  |       +--------------------------------------------------+       |
  |       |                 <secure storage>                 |       |
  |       |                                                  |       |
  |       |  map of device identifiers to login credentials  |       |
  |       +--------------------------------------------------+       |
  |                                                                  |
  +------------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>In order to authenticate the device, the NMS
          MUST possess the  X.509 certificate for the trust anchor 
          leading to the device's entity certificate.  The NMS 
          uses this certificate to validate the server-certificate 
          the device presents during SSH or TLS transport negotiation.
          Because an NMS may interoperate with multiple vendors, and
          a vendor may have more than one trust anchor for signing
          its devices IDevID certificates, this generalizes into
          the NMS needing a list of trust anchor certificates.
          This certificates SHOULD be stored in a way that prevents
          tampering, which is why they are shown in immutable
          storage in the diagram.</t>
          <t>In order for the NMS to validate that the specific
          device connecting to it is expected, it MUST have
          a list of unique device identifiers that it can use
          to validate the device's IDevID certificate with.
          The list SHOULD be protected from external modification,
          which is why it is shown in immutable storage in the
          diagram.  In order for the NMS to know the unique 
          identifiers, device manufacturers will need to provide
          a mechanism to convey this information to its customers.
          This draft not specify a format for this information exchange.</t>
          <t>In addition to authenticating the device, the NMS must
          also authenticate itself to the device.  How this is done
          is deployment specific, but generalizes to the NMS needing
          to have login credentials for each device.  These credentials
          will entail knowing a secret (e.g., password, private key).
          For this reason the diagram shows the NMS storing a map of
          device credentials in secure storage.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Connection Handling">
          <t>When receiving a NETCONF call home connection from a
          device, the NSM completes the connection as specified 
          NETCONF Call Home <xref target="NETCONF-CALL-HOME"/>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Vendor" anchor="vendor">
        <section title="Order Information" anchor="order-information">
          <t>In order for a Vendor's customers to configure their 
          NMSs with what devices are expected, as well as to know how to
          set the "unique-identifier" field within a Configlet
          when requesting a signing, Vendors need to provide a 
          mechanism for customers to obtain the unique 
          identifier value for the devices they have
          ordered.  For instance, customers could receive emails
          containing shipping information for their devices.</t>
          <t>Additionally, to facilitate workflows where the
          devices are initially received by a customer-specific
          warehouse, or moved after having been unboxed, it is 
          ideal for the unique identifier to be easily tracked
          through labels affixed to the device as well as the box
          it is packaged in.  A device's serial number is commonly
          treated this way and would be suitable for this purpose,
          so long as it is directly related to its IDevID identity.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Ownership Validation">
          <t>In order for Configuration Signers to validate that a
          requestor is the true owner of a device (i.e. its IDevID
          identity), Vendors need to provide a mechanism enabling
          a near real-time lookup.  The interface used to implement
          this lookup is outside the scope of this document.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Configlet" anchor="configlet">
        <section title="Overview" anchor="configlet-overview">
          <t>A Configlet is an XML file, containing specific YANG-defined 
          configuration, that has been signed by a trusted signer known to
          the device (e.g., the device's manufacturer).</t>
          <t>The Configlet data-model, defined by the XSD schema in 
          <xref target="configlet-xsd-schema"/>, contains information for 
          the device to ensure that it's safe for it to load the configlet 
          (i.e. target-requirements) along with a payload, the configuration
          the device is to merge into its running datastore.</t>
          <t>In order for the device to call home, the configuration
          contained within the Configlet MUST at least configure a local user 
          account and configure the connection information for the NMS the 
          device is to call home to.   This configuration MAY use IETF-defined 
          modules "ietf-system" <xref target="RFC7317"/> and 
          "ietf-netconf-server" <xref target="NETCONF-SERVER-MODEL"/>.</t>
          <t>The signature on the Configlet is enveloped, 
          meaning that the signature is contained inside the
          XML file itself.  The signature block also contains
          the X.509 certificate of the Configuration Signer
          and its chain of trust.</t>
          <t>Once a device authenticates the signature on a
          Configlet and matches the unique identifier
          (e.g., serial number) within the Configlet, it merges
          the configuration contained in the Configlet into
          its running datastore.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Data Model" anchor="configlet-data-model">
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ietf-netconf-zerotouch.yang.tree)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>The Configlet's data model is no more than a wrapper
          around a header (i.e. &lt;target-requirements&gt;) and a 
          payload (i.e. &lt;configuration&gt;).</t>
          <t>The &lt;target-requirements&gt; element contains
          information that MUST be validated by the device
          prior to processing the  &lt;configuration&gt; element.
          Specifically, it contains:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>unique-identifier
                <list style="empty">
                  <t>The unique-identifier field is used to ensure that
                  the Configlet is loaded onto the targeted device
                  and no other.  This field is also used by the
                  Configuration Signer, when ensuring the requestor
                  is the true owner of the device.  The value MUST
                  be the same as the 'subject' field in the device's
                  IDevID credential, as specified by section 7.2.8 in
                  IEEE Std 802.1AR-2009.</t>
                </list>
              </t>
              <t>software-version
                <list style="empty">
                  <t>The software-version field is used to ensure
                  the device is running the right software version
                  prior to loading the configuration (e.g., 14.1R2.5).
                  If the device finds that it is not running the 
                  correct version of software, it MUST pull the 
                  correct version from the Configuration Server.</t>
                </list>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>The &lt;configuration&gt; element contains the configuration
          that is to be committed to the device's running datastore.  This
          element uses the "anyxml" type, enabling it to contain either
          vendor-specific or standards-based data models.  When using
          standard models, in order to complete a call home connection,
          only the following is needed:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>The "authentication" subtree from "ietf-system", defined in <xref target="RFC7317"/>.</t>
              <t>The "call-home" subtree from "ietf-netconf-server", defined in <xref target="NETCONF-SERVER-MODEL"/>.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Signature">
          <t>All Configlets MUST be signed by a Configuration Signer
          in order to be authentic.  Devices MUST reject any Configlet
          that is either unsigned or having an invalid signature.
          Configlets are signed using the W3C standard
          "XML Signature Syntax and Processing" <xref target="XMLSIG"/>.
          The entire contents of the Configlet MUST be signed.  The
          signature block must also include the Configuration Signer's 
          certificate and any intermediate certificates leading to 
          a Configuration Signer trust anchor.  A signed Configlet 
          example is in section <xref target="signed-configlet"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Encryption (optional)">
          <t>Configlets MAY optionally be encrypted prior to being
          signed.  Encrypting the Configlet provides confidentiality
          for the Configlet's contents without relying on transport-level
          security.  Configlets are encrypted using the W3C standard
          "XML Encryption Syntax and Processing" <xref target="XMLENC"/>.
          The entire contents of the Configlet MUST be encrypted.
          An encrypted Configlet example is in section 
          <xref target="signed-encrypted-configlet"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="XSD Schema" anchor="configlet-xsd-schema">
          <t>
            <figure>
              <preamble>Following is the XSD for the Configlet:</preamble>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(ietf-netconf-zerotouch-configlet.xsd)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-con">
        <section title="Immutable storage for trust anchors">
          <t>Devices SHOULD ensure that all its trust anchor 
          certificates, including those for the Configuration 
          Signer and Configuration Server, are protected from
          external modification.  It is for this reason that
          the diagram in <xref target="device-precondition"/>
          shows them in immutable storage.</t>
          <t>However, it may be necessary to update these 
          certificates over time (e.g., the vendor wants to
          delegate trust to a new CA).  It is therefore expected
          that devices MAY update these trust anchors when 
          needed through a verifiable process, such as a 
          software upgrade using signed software images.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Substitutions">
          <t>It is generally not possible to substitute a 
          Configlet created for a different device, since 
          devices assert that the Configlet contains their 
          unique identifier (e.g., serial number).</t>
          <t>However, it is possible to substitute a Configlet 
          created for a device with a different Configlet 
          created for the same device.  Generally, unless 
          imposed by the Configuration Signers, there is no
          limit to the number of Configlets that may be
          generated for a given device.  This could be resolved, in 
          part, by placing a timestamp into the Configlet and 
          ensuring devices do not load Configlets older than some 
          amount, but this requires the devices have an accurate 
          clock when validating a Configlet and for Configuration 
          Signers to not sign a Configlet when another Configlet
          is still active.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Confidentiality">
          <t>This draft allows devices to use insecure schemes when
          doing a Configuration Server lookup.  This is deemed 
          acceptable because the Configlet is tamper-proof, since
          it MUST be signed, only confidentiality is lost.</t>
          <t>Confidentiality of a Configlet's contents is assured
          when either the Configlet is encrypted or when the a 
          secure scheme is used when accessing the Configuration Server.</t>
          <t>Some confidentiality is lost when an insecure scheme is
          used to access a Configuration Server, as then the device's
          unique identifier is in the clear.</t>
          <t>Given the fairly regular format for unique identifiers,
          it is possible that an adversary to guess unique identifiers
          and access a device's Configlet.  Configlets that have been
          encrypted do not disclose any confidential information.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Entropy loss over time">
          <t>Section 7.2.7.2 of the IEEE Std 802.1AR-2009 standard says
          that IDevID certificate should never expire (i.e. having a
          notAfter 99991231235959Z).  Given the long-lived
          nature of these certificates, it is paramount to use a 
          strong key length (e.g., 512-bit ECC).   Vendors SHOULD
          deploy Online Certificate State Protocol (OCSP) responders 
          or CRL Distribution Points (CDP) to revoke certificates in 
          case necessary.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Serial Numbers">
          <t>This draft mentions using the device's serial number as
          its unique identifier in its IDevID certificate.  This is 
          because serial numbers are ubiquitous and prominently 
          contained in invoices and on labels affixed to devices and
          their packaging.  That said, serial numbers many times encode
          revealing information, such as the device's model number,
          manufacture date, and/or sequence number.  Knowledge of this
          information may provide an adversary with details needed 
          to launch an attack.  To address this concern, the 
          certificate could contain the hash of the serial number
          instead, which the NMS could also compute, but doing so 
          is much less intuitive and raises questions if it is just
          security through obscurity.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations">
        <section title="ZeroTouch Information DHCP Option" anchor="zerotouch-info-option">
          <t>The following registration is in accordance to RFC 2939 for
          "BOOTP Vendor Extensions and DHCP Options" registry maintained at
          http://www.iana.org/assignments/bootp-dhcp-parameters.</t>
          <section title="DHCP v4 Option">
            <figure>
              <artwork>
   Tag: XXX

   Name: Zero Touch Information

   Description: Returns a list of null-terminated Configuration 
                Server URIs

    Code   Len
   +-----+-----+------+------+----
   | XXX |  n  | url1 | url2 | ...
   +-----+-----+------+------+----

   Reference: RFC XXXX
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>
          <section title="DHCP v6 Option">
            <figure>
              <artwork>
   Tag: YYY

   Name: Zero Touch Information

   Description: Returns a list of null-terminated Configuration 
                Server URIs

    Code   Len
   +-----+-----+------+------+----
   | YYY |  n  | url1 | url2 | ...
   +-----+-----+------+------+----

   Reference: RFC XXXX
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Media Types for Boot Images and Configurations" anchor="zerotouch-media-types">
          <t>The following registrations are in accordance to RFC 6838.</t>
          <section title="application/zerotouch-configlet">
            <figure>
              <artwork>
 
   Type name: application

   Subtype name: zerotouch-configlet

   Required parameters: None

   Optional parameters: None

   Encoding considerations: 8-bit

   Security considerations: See Security Considerations in RFC XXXX

   Interoperability considerations: None

   Published specification: RFC XXXX

   Applications that use this media type:

      Configuration servers and NETCONF servers.

   Fragment identifier considerations: None

   Additional information:

     Deprecated alias names for this type: N/A
     Magic number(s): None
     File extension(s): xml
     Macintosh file type code(s): 'TEXT'

   Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:
      Kent Watsen &lt;kwatsen@juniper.net&gt;

   Intended usage: COMMON

   Restrictions on usage: None

   Author:
     This specification is a work item of the IETF NETCONF working 
     group, with mailing list address &lt;netconf@ietf.org&gt;.

   Change controller: The IESG &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;

   Provisional registration? (standards tree only): No
              </artwork>
            </figure>

          </section>
          <section title="application/zerotouch-bootimage">
            <figure>
              <artwork>

   Type name: application

   Subtype name: zerotouch-bootimage

   Required parameters: None

   Optional parameters: None

   Encoding considerations: binary

   Security considerations: See Security Considerations in RFC XXXX

   Interoperability considerations: None

   Published specification: RFC XXXX

   Applications that use this media type:

      Configuration servers and NETCONF servers.

   Fragment identifier considerations: None

   Additional information:

     Deprecated alias names for this type: N/A
     Magic number(s): None
     File extension(s): None
     Macintosh file type code(s): N/A

   Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:
      Kent Watsen &lt;kwatsen@juniper.net&gt;

   Intended usage: COMMON

   Restrictions on usage: None

   Author:
     This specification is a work item of the IETF NETCONF working 
     group, with mailing list address &lt;netconf@ietf.org&gt;.

   Change controller: The IESG &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;

   Provisional registration? (standards tree only): No
              </artwork>
            </figure>

          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Acknowledgements">
        <t>The authors would like to thank for following for
        lively discussions on list and in the halls (ordered
        by last name): 
        David Harrington,
        Dean Bogdanovic,
        Martin Bjorklund,
        Wes Hardaker,
        Russ Mundy,
        Reinaldo Penno,
        Randy Presuhn,
        Juergen Schoenwaelder.</t>
          
        <t>Special thanks goes to Russ Mundy and Wes Hardaker
        for brainstorming the original I-D's solution during
        the IETF 87 meeting in Berlin.</t>
      </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            &rfc2119;
            &rfc6187;

            <!-- &rfc7317;  - why isn't this working!  below is the same as fetched by the URL! -->
<reference anchor="RFC7317">
<front>
<title>A YANG Data Model for System Management</title>
<author initials="A." surname="Bierman" fullname="A. Bierman">
<organization/>
</author>
<author initials="M." surname="Bjorklund" fullname="M. Bjorklund">
<organization/>
</author>
<date year="2014" month="August"/>
<abstract>
<t>
This document defines a YANG data model for the configuration and identification of some common system properties within a device containing a Network Configuration Protocol (NETCONF) server. This document also includes data node definitions for system identification, time-of-day management, user management, DNS resolver configuration, and some protocol operations for system management.
</t>
</abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7317"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="60119" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7317.txt"/>
</reference>

            <reference anchor="Std-802.1AR-2009" target="http://standards.ieee.org/findstds/standard/802.1AR-2009.html">
                <front>
                    <title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks - Secure Device Identity</title>
                    <author fullname="WG802.1 - Higher Layer LAN Protocols Working Group">
                        <organization>IEEE SA-Standards Board</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="December" year="2009"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="XMLSIG" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmldsig-core1">
                <front>
                    <title>XML Signature Syntax and Processing</title>
                    <author fullname="World Wide Web Consortium"></author>
                    <date month="April" year="2013"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="XMLENC" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlenc-core1">
                <front>
                    <title>XML Encryption Syntax and Processing</title>
                    <author fullname="World Wide Web Consortium"></author>
                    <date month="April" year="2013"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="NETCONF-CALL-HOME" target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-netconf-call-home-01">
                <front>
                    <title>NETCONF Call Home (work in progress)</title>
                    <author initials="K.W." surname="Watsen"
                            fullname="Kent Watsen">
                        <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="October" year="2014"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="NETCONF-SERVER-MODEL" target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-netconf-server-model-03">
                <front>
                    <title>NETCONF Server Model (work in progress)</title>
                    <author initials="K.W." surname="Watsen"
                            fullname="Kent Watsen">
                        <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="September" year="2014"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

        </references>
        <references title="Informative References">

            <reference anchor="TR069" target="http://www.broadband-forum.org/technical/download/TR-069_Amendment-3.pdf">
                <front>
                    <title>
                        TR-069 Amendment 3, CPE WAN Management Protocol
                    </title>
                    <author surname="The Broadband Forum" 
                            fullname="The Broadband Forum"/>
                    <date month="November" year="2010" />
                </front>
            </reference>

        </references>
        <section title="Examples" anchor="examples">
            <section title="Unsigned Configlet" anchor="unsigned-configlet">
              <t>
                <figure>
                    <preamble>
                      This example illustrates a Configlet
                      configuring both a local user account and
                      call home using SSH.

                      Note, this is not a valid Configlet because it isn't signed.
                    </preamble>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-configlet.xml)
]]></artwork>
                </figure>
              </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Signed Configlet" anchor="signed-configlet">
                <t>
                <figure>
                    <preamble>
                      This example illustrates the above unsigned Configlet
                      signed as if by a Configuration Signer. Note
                      that in addition to the signature itself, the
                      signed Configlet embeds two certificates, the
                      chain of certificates from the signer's certificate
                      up to but not including the trust anchor certificate.
                    </preamble>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-configlet-signed.xml)
]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Encrypted Configlet" anchor="encrypted-configlet">
                <t>
                <figure>
                    <preamble>
                      This example illustrates the above unsigned Configlet
                      that has been encrypted using the device's public key.

                      Note, this is not a valid Configlet because it isn't signed.
                    </preamble>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-configlet-encrypted.xml)
]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                </t>
            </section>


            <section title="Signed Encrypted Configlet" anchor="signed-encrypted-configlet">
                <t>
                <figure>
                    <preamble>
                      This example illstrates the above encrypted Configlet
                      that has been signed by a Configuration Signer's
                      private key.
                    </preamble>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/ex-configlet-encrypted-signed.xml)
]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                </t>
            </section>

        </section>

        <section title="Change Log">
          <section title="ID to 00">
            <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Major structural update; the essence is the same.
              Most every section was rewritten to some degree.</t>
              <t>Added a Use Cases section</t>
              <t>Added diagrams for "Actors and Roles" and
              "NMS Precondition" sections, and greatly improved
              the "Device Boot Sequence" diagram</t>
              <t>Removed support for physical presence or any
              ability for Configlets to not be signed.</t>
              <t>Defined the ZeroTouch Information DHCP option</t>
              <t>Added an ability for devices to also download
              images from Configuration Servers</t>
              <t>Added an ability for Configlets to be encrypted</t>
              <t>Now Configuration Servers only have to support
              HTTP/S - no other schemes possible</t>
            </list>
            </t>
          </section>
          <section title="00 to 01">
            <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Added boot-image and validate-owner annotations
                 to the "Actors and Roles" diagram.</t>
              <t>Fixed 2nd paragrph in section 7.1 to reflect 
                 current use of anyxml.</t>
              <t>Added encrypted and signed-encrypted examples</t>
              <t>Replaced YANG module with XSD schema</t>
              <t>Added IANA request for the ZeroTouch Information DHCP Option</t>
              <t>Added IANA request for media types for boot-image and configuration</t>
            </list>
            </t>
          </section>


        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>

